Let's pray.
Should have given a trigger warning on the bumper. I keep forgetting. It's pretty intense.
Welcome, again, to week seven of our series, "Through the Book of Revelation," everyone's favorite book.
We'll throw out that graphic one more time. Actually, probably not one more time. We'll keep coming back to it.
This is kind of the framework that we've talked about with the Book of Revelation, that Revelation is a...
We'll see the heaven kind of opened up, that Revelation is a revealing, an opening of the curtain,
so that the churches in Asia Minor that were being persecuted in the first century could understand what was happening
after the resurrection and ascension of Jesus and before the coming return.
We've said that we've used this language of inaugurated and consummated, right?
That Jesus inaugurated his kingdom and his resurrection and ascension, everything.
Jarrett said this morning that Satan has been defeated, and yet he is flailing, and that causes lots of chaos and destruction.
In our worlds until Jesus returns. The goal of this revelation, this revealing, is to challenge churches that are rebelling against God's kingdom because of the persecution that they're facing.
To wake up churches that have become stagnant, that have become compromised, that have kind of found themselves just going with the flow of the current of our culture.
And if I were to put the American church in any of these categories, that's probably the one that we are most tempted to struggle with, to just go with the flow of what life is all about.
And lastly, it's to encourage the persecuted church to remind them everything Jared said this morning, that the victory has been won.
So we are rounding third base at this point, headed home through the book of Revelation.
And if you are a part of our newsletter, you will have seen that Kent is preaching the last sermon in two weeks.
And he wants your feedback. So if you get on the newsletter, we'd love for you to think about that.
Because at the beginning of Revelation, oh, we got a QR code slide. See, our tech team is the best, right?
Our office staff, the best. They just do things that I don't even know they're doing.
And so if you want to grab that QR code, at the beginning of the book of Revelation,
John opens with this declaration that his goal is that the churches would keep the words of this prophecy.
And I've said throughout this series that I think oftentimes the way that we study the book of Revelation is more about reading our newspapers
and trying to figure out where we're at and the cycles of all the things that John's prophesying.
And the problem with that is that it doesn't typically have application for our lives.
If anything, it just makes us afraid or confused or it's cynical or whatever, but it doesn't wake us up, encourage us, challenge us.
And what we want to do with this series is look at the book of Revelation the way that it was intended
and figure out what does it look like for us to keep these words of the prophecy.
So put some thought into that. Give Kent a hundred, he asked for 170 words or less of how this is stirring your mind
and your heart about how to keep it. I tried to do it in 170 words or less. It did not end well for me.
Hopefully you do better than I do. Cool. All right. So we're going to be in just a minute after I pray,
we're going to get to the last cycle of sevens that we've been going through.
There's the seven seals, then the seven trumpets, and now the seven bowls.
And I just want to remind us, an important reminder this week, that these images are highly symbolic.
Another problem with the way that oftentimes we try and interpret Revelation is we look for literal manifestations of these images on earth.
They're highly symbolic images. The example I like to give is like John saw Jesus as a lamb, though slain.
That is a true image of the person and character of Jesus. But do I think when we get to heaven that Jesus will look like a lamb slain, or will he have a resurrected, glorified body?
I think probably a resurrected, glorified body, but the symbol of the image is intended to communicate something to us.
The same with these seven seals and trumpets and bowls. There's lots of imagery and lots of stuff going on.
We should not be looking for a literal manifestation of this. The best illustration that I've seen in the commentaries,
do they talk about political cartoons? You guys into political cartoons? Anybody? Okay. Probably not.
Some of you have never held a newspaper before, and it shows. It shows. Political cartoons, they have images of real figures,
but they're wildly dramatized and changed and adapted to try and get a point across.
And that's what John is doing with his images here in Revelation. He's giving you graphics and image for you to bring to mind,
but he's not asking you to look for literal manifestations of these things on earth.
He's asking you to see what is happening in the spiritual world behind the physical things on earth.
Is that tracking? Okay. Hopefully it makes sense later. Let's pray. We'll get started.
Father in heaven, we thank you for another opportunity to gather together to peel back the curtain on our experience of your kingdom on earth until you come.
God, there's a lot of challenging images in the book of Revelation.
Probably the ones we're going to look at today rival the most challenging of the whole book.
And so I just pray that you would prepare our hearts and give us eyes to see what you actually want us to see.
That you would wake us up, encourage us, challenge us to put these words into practice.
God, so that your church would more clearly demonstrate your kingdom as it is in heaven on earth until you come.
In Jesus name I pray. Amen.
Can you guys help me test some of my pet peeves out? I need a sanity check for my own anger issues.
So can we do a little crowd participation this morning?
I'm going to go through, you didn't even say yes.
Okay. I don't want to assume. I'm not paying you all the hourly rate that I pay my therapist, but, I mean, I'll pay one hourly rate.
You guys can divvy it up, and maybe you'll get a quarter or something. It'll be great.
Okay. So I'm going to give you some of the things that make me angry, and you tell me whether or not my responses are justified or whether or not I should probably just let it go. Okay?
Somebody is going slow in the passing lane. Am I allowed to tailgate and high beam them?
You guys, okay. Or should I let it go? Okay, okay. Somebody in the grocery line in front of me has 18 items in the 10 item or less line.
Do I get close to their back and say one, two, three? Or do I let it go? Okay.
This one really makes me mad. When people ride their bikes down a walking sidewalk, am I allowed to, like, give them a little juke?
And if they fall, they fall. If not, or should I let it go? You guys are bad influences.
Last, this one Merson and I had recently at airport security. When every announcement leading up to me getting to the airport security tells me that I have to take my shoes off,
and I'm taking my shoes off, and the airport security person looks at me like I'm a moron and says, "You don't have to take your shoes off."
Do I just slowly keep taking my shoes off, or do I let it go?
All right, I think most of these fall into the category of let it go and see a counselor, Ryan.
But, all right, now what if I found out that there was someone on our accounting team that was stealing money from the church offering?
What if I found out someone in our church was cheating on their spouse and hiding it?
What if I found out that Rory's daycare workers were abusing him?
Do we feel the emotional shift in the room?
That's interesting to me because apparently anger isn't inherently good or bad.
A lot of it depends on what we're angry about and how we go about addressing that anger.
Which calls out the tension that I think we're going to see as we hop into Revelation chapter 15 and 16.
Revelation 15 and 16 is probably the place where we see this tension the loudest in the entire Scriptures.
We read about something that most modern people, including many Christians, including myself at many times in my life, are really uncomfortable talking about: the wrath of God.
And if we're going to understand what I think John wants us to understand in his symbolic imagery,
we're going to have to decide whether or not God's wrath is an embarrassing ancient Christian idea that we need to explain away.
Or is it possible that we've misunderstood something important about God, his character, our sin, and his love for the world?
So I want to hop into these chapters. I want to pull that thread a little bit and see if it's possible that maybe we're kind of missing what the Scriptures want us to see in regards to God's wrath.
Again, in chapters 15, 16, we're going to encounter this third set of sevens, and I know if you brought your friend to church this morning, you're like, "Seriously, Ryan?
I finally got him to come, and you're going to preach on the wrath of God?" Just give me like 30 minutes, and hopefully it'll make sense.
All right, chapter 15, 16, the third set of sevens we've been working through the past weeks, the seals, the trumpets, the bowls.
And I'm not going to spend much time on the specifics of the seven bowls and what they are and what they mean, partially because most scholars believe that these three sets of sevens are a retelling and a, you guys want to learn a fancy Bible scholar word?
Okay, recapitulation. Okay, that's what the scholars call it, a recapitulation.
It's John kind of sharing the same events from different angles, and he's crescendoing the intensification of them.
He's making them feel more weighty, more heavy, more dramatic in order to wake up the people of God and the people of the earth.
These seven bowls are going to parallel, in many ways, the plagues of Egypt during the Exodus.
So these people were steeped in the Old Testament Scriptures. They're immediately going to be inputting and downloading the story of the Exodus.
And I know for some of us, we can do that because we grew up in church and we went to Sunday school.
Some of us maybe will struggle with some of that, but just know that in the backdrop of this story is the plagues of Egypt.
They were directed at the people of the earth. These bowls are just like the plagues were directed at the people of Egypt.
And Pharaoh who had hardened their hearts to God's warning and refused to repent of their wicked ways.
And interestingly enough, what we're going to see in the seven bowls is this is the first set of seven where it seems like the people of God are outside of the experience of the difficulty of what's going on.
The seven seals and the seven trumpets, the people of God, the faithful people of God are experiencing the difficulty and challenges.
They are crying out to God, "How long, O Lord, will you allow these things to happen?"
And when we get to chapter 15 and 16, we're going to see that the people of God are actually outside the experience of the wrath of God.
Let's just hop in and see if I can make this make sense in the next 30 minutes.
Okay. I've been struggling, just so you know. Okay. Real people realize.
Chapter 15, verse 1, "I saw in heaven another great and marvelous sign, seven angels with seven last plagues, last because with them God's wrath is," say it with me, "completed.
And I saw what looked like a sea of glass glowing with fire and standing beside the sea."
NIV translates it beside the sea. I don't like that translation.
The literal Greek is actually on the sea. The people of God are standing on the sea.
That should communicate something to us. Again, we've talked about how waters throughout the time of the early readers, they represented chaos and death and hardship.
And now God's people are standing on top of the sea of chaos, which is intended to represent death and chaos.
They are standing victorious and conquering over that chaos. I saw them standing on the sea of glass.
Those who had been victorious over the beast and its image and over the number of its name, they held harps given to them by God.
They sang song of God's servant Moses and of the lamb. They said this, "Great and marvelous are your deeds, Lord God Almighty.
Just and true are your ways, King of all the nations, who will not fear you, Lord, and bring glory to your name, for you are holy.
All the nations will come and worship before you, for your righteous acts have been revealed."
And then we turn to chapter 16 and we read this in verse 5, "Then I heard the angel in charge of the waters,
the waters that the believers are standing on, say, 'You are just in these judgments, O holy one,
you who are and who were, for they have shed the blood, the people of earth have shed the blood of your holy people
and your prophets, and you have given them blood to drink as they deserve.' And I heard the altar respond,
'Yes, Lord Almighty, true and just are your judgments.'"
So here we see the faithful people of God, not just passing through the waters of chaos,
but literally standing victoriously on the waters of chaos, singing a worship song to the Lamb,
who has revealed the righteousness of God, the justice and grace, the judgment and mercy of God in His person and work and character.
And we hear the altar saying, "True and just are your judgments."
We could input the word wrath there, "True and just is your wrath."
Wrath, which leads me to the first point as we kind of pull this thread,
this tension that we're feeling about God's anger towards sin and the chaos and destruction the dragon is bringing the earth.
My first point here is that God's wrath is good because God is good.
And again, most of us do not like the idea of wrath until we think about the alternative,
until we think about someone cheating on their spouse and hiding it and me as a person
knowing about it and doing nothing. So we think about a vulnerable child being abused by those
who are supposed to be taking care of them and somebody who has a position to stop it doing nothing.
When we think about the alternative of righteous anger not existing,
what would it be for an all-powerful and loving God to ignore the injustice of a broken world?
The evil that is influenced by the dragon and seeks to distort God's good creation,
the evil that is intent on taking what God created for life in abundance and using it to steal, kill, and destroy.
I love this scholar, Leon Morris, how he defines God's wrath. He says, "God's wrath is a strong and settled opposition to all that is evil."
We could expand that definition to say a strong and settled opposition to all that seeks to destroy God's good creation.
The same reason the Israelites could sing the song of Moses after watching the Red Sea swallow the Egyptian army is the same reason the faithful people of God can rejoice at God's wrath being poured out on the unrepentant inhabitants of the earth.
Because we know sufficient warning has been given, a sufficient way out has been offered.
And yet many people remain unmoved in partnership with the dragon and his schemes to destroy God's good world through their sinful actions.
So if we really think about the weight of sin and the way it impacts creation, if we understand the weight of God's love for his creation and his desire for it to produce life and flourishing and we look all around us.
And we've talked about this for the past few weeks, the way in which people of the earth partner with the dragon to take what was created for good and to distort it for evil.
Then we can understand how the people of God who have cried out, "How long, O Lord, will you allow this to happen?"
That when judgment and wrath is finally poured out to its completion, you can understand how the people of God could take a sigh of relief and say, "True and just are your ways."
It's not that we're happy about wrath. It's that we realize the result of letting sin go unchecked.
I don't think any good, faithful follower of Jesus would be in their bones excited about God pouring out judgment.
But we understand the alternative. We understand that the God who pours out this justice is good.
I love how N.T. Wright illustrates it in his short commentary on Revelation. I'm paraphrasing because I didn't want to quote two pages.
Actually, I did want to quote two pages, but I felt like there might be some copyright issues there.
He says this, "Imagine a small village on the outskirts of town where injustice keeps piling up.
A worker is cheated, a widow is stolen from, a family is exploited, and someone is falsely accused.
But there's no one around with the authority to make it right.
Finally, after months of building frustration and hopelessness, the district judge makes his way to the town.
He will hear each case properly and fairly. He will steadfastly refuse all bribes, and he will make his judgment.
For the oppressor, that's bad news. But for everyone who's been suffering and even dying under the weight of unchecked injustice, it's wonderful news.
Wright says, "Now take that village and magnify it up to the global level," and this is what we're talking about when we talk about the biblical idea of judgment.
God, through Jesus, comes to confront all that is destroying his good creation, and he intends to put all things to right.
I think when we begin to realize the level of injustice and death that is brought to the world by the dragon and all who wear his mark,
and the level of love and holiness contained in the character of God,
we can begin to say with the altar, "True and just are your judgments."
Do we understand? Do we catch glimpses of the beauty of God's creation and the goodness of sacrificial love poured out to the vulnerable?
Do we see the goodness of God's creation? And do we see all the areas all over the world
where it is being attacked and taken advantage of, and where people who are vulnerable are being used for their ability to create wealth,
and then those who are abusing them are taking advantage of that. And we can see the ways in which leaving this unchecked
would not be good for a God who is good and loved. God's wrath is good because God is good and because evil exists.
The second thing I want to point out from these two chapters is that God desires, his desire is repentance, not rejection.
That the reason we don't get the wrath of God until chapter 15 is because John is trying to demonstrate the thing that God
has been trying to demonstrate to people throughout all creation, and that God is wanting a relationship with his people,
that he's inviting all creation into right relationship with him, that he's given them a free way out of his wrath and his judgment,
and that he's inviting them to participate in the goodness of his creation.
God is slow and patient and kind, and he does not desire repentance, or he does desire repentance, not rejection,
and yet he is met over and over again with rejection from the people of the earth. Verse 9, they respond.
It says, "But they refused to repent and glorify God." Again, he's pouring out this judgment. He's pouring out these warnings.
He's trying to get their attention, and they refused to repent and to glorify him.
Again, in verse 11, they refused to repent of what they had done. And then in verse 21, they cursed God on account of the plagues because of how terrible they were.
And I think Pastor Sam, a few weeks ago, did such a great job unpacking this idea in the message of the seven trumpets.
The point of John's intensifying symbols is to show that God is desperately trying to get the attention of those who have been deceived and coerced into submission to the dragon.
And his counterfeit kingdom. That the intensification of the warnings is God's love for these people who have been deceived and coerced.
He's trying to get them to see there's a better way. Like a loving father who's pleading with his son to give up the behaviors that are killing him and his family and those around him.
And there is a real tension here where maybe some of you in the room are like, "Ryan, I don't struggle with the tension of God's wrath.
The thing that I struggle with is the tension of why it's taking him so long." Some of you who have been used and abused and taken advantage of, some of you have had horrific things done to you.
And you see the people who did the horrific things to you, and you see them seemingly flourishing, and you see you dealing with the consequences of the actions that they did against you.
And your question to me and to the Bible is not, "Why does God have wrath?" Your question is, "Why is his wrath taking so long?"
And the answer to that question is that God is a loving and patient Father.
2 Peter frames it up this way. This is Eugene Peterson's quotation, or his translation of it.
It says this, "Don't overlook the obvious here, friends. With God, one day is as good as a thousand years, and a thousand years as a day. God isn't late with his promise, as some measure lateness.
He is restraining himself on account of you, holding back the end because he doesn't want anyone lost. He's giving everyone space and time to change.
But when the day of God's judgment does come, it will be unannounced like a thief. The sky will collapse with a thunderous bang and everything disintegrating in a raging inferno.
The earth and all its work exposed to the scrutiny of judgment. God is slow and patient and kind.
He does not want any to perish, but to all would experience life and life everlasting.
He has a deep desire for every human being created in his image to understand what life and life more abundantly looks like.
So whichever side of the wrath tension you struggle with, the Scripture is intent on you seeing God's goodness in the middle of it.
If you struggle with there being wrath at all, the Scripture wants you to think about the alternative.
What would a world look like where a just, good, loving God lets sin go unpunished?
And again, when we hear sin, oftentimes we think about the ticky-tacky things that maybe a religious community put their thumb on us for.
But we need to zoom out and see the ways in which our participation with sin and sin kind of spreading throughout creation actually causes death and destruction for people all over the place.
So for those of us that struggle with wrath, we need to understand that God is just so patient and kind.
And for those of us that are just like, "Yeah, He's not doing it soon enough. I need it now. I need relief now. I need justice now."
We need to see God's patience and His goodness and see His patience with us and want that experience for those who don't yet have it.
The tragedy of Revelation 15 and 16 isn't God's unwillingness to save, but humanity's unwillingness to receive that salvation.
This is the tragedy that God is continually extending salvation, offering forgiveness and grace, and humanity is looking the other way and saying, "We're good."
God's righteous wrath is an outpouring of His love for people and His desire for the redemption of His creation.
Again, Peterson's translation of a famous verse that we like to quote, John 3:16,
but if we carry it through, it gives us some real clarity here. John 3:16-19, it says,
"This is how much God loved the world. He gave His Son, His one and only Son,
and this is why, so that no one need be destroyed. By believing in Him, anyone can have whole and lasting life."
God didn't go to all the trouble of sending His Son to merely point an accusing finger, telling the world how bad it was.
He came to help, to put the world right again. Anyone who trusts in Him is acquitted.
Anyone who refuses to trust Him has long since been under the death sentence without knowing it.
And why? Because of that person's failure to believe in the one-of-a-kind Son of God when introduced to Him.
This is the crisis we're in. This is the tension we're experiencing.
God light streamed into the world, but men and women everywhere ran for the darkness.
This is the tension we're in. God brought light into the world through His Son, Jesus,
and the world crucified Him. This is human sin's response to God's goodness.
Kill and run away. Run from the light into the darkness.
And what is a holy, righteous, and loving God to do with a people who literally crucified His Son,
the perfect image of His goodness and love and forgiveness?
And they didn't crucify Him because of His harshness. They crucified Him because their desire to be in control.
In Jesus, we see God's love collide with humanity's sin. His crucifixion demonstrates our love of darkness rather than light.
God's wrath is inevitable because of His goodness and the evil that our sin perpetuates.
But His desire is repentance, not rejection. He is slow and patient and kind.
And He is trying to get our attention to see His goodness in the midst of wrath.
You guys hanging in there? All right, good. Well, it's going to get, it gets better starting now, I think.
The third point I want to emphasize here from Revelation 15 and 16 is that God's wrath will come to an end.
And these chapters are, I think, the most important thing that we can do when interpreting these two chapters is see the phrases that they're bracketed by.
Again, this is a new scene that starts in 15 and ends at the end of 16, and it starts with these words, "God's wrath is completed."
As the bowls are being poured out, the declaration is that God's wrath is coming to an end, and then the chapters end in chapter 16, verse 17.
"The seventh angel poured out his bowl, the last bowl, into the air, and out of the temple came a loud voice from the throne saying, 'It is done.'"
And if we've read the Gospels, this should be triggering something in our minds and in our hearts.
We should be thinking about the crucifixion scene. We should be thinking about the death of Christ, where Jesus, hanging on the cross, declared, "It is finished."
The work of God's eternal redemption plan for all creation was completed on that blessed and Good Friday.
Our Lord rested from his eternal work on Saturday, was raised on Sunday. A few weeks later, ascended to his rightful place on the throne,
where he sounds like a lion who is roaring, but he looks like a lamb who has been slain.
The work of Jesus is the culmination of God's kingdom.
The redemption of God solidified. Revelation is showing us what must happen between the inauguration and consummation of that kingdom.
It's not pretty because the dragon is flailing. Remember a couple weeks ago, the dragon was thrown.
Okay, you were better last week, not terrible this week. I didn't really set you up super good either.
The dragon was thrown. He has ultimately been defeated, but he is still flailing and causing chaos and destruction.
And it's in this in-between time of sin ultimately coming to its culmination in the crucifixion of the image of God.
And God's patiently waiting for all people to come to repentance. It's in this in-between stage.
Where we deal with this tension of God having wrath, or how long is God's wrath going to take?
And it's in these chapters that we see the good news that God's wrath will come to an end.
If I had to summarize it, I'd say it this way. Before sin existed, God was love.
Because sin exists, God has wrath towards evil. And when final, and when evil is finally dealt with,
and every tear is wiped away from our eyes, God will still be love.
My main point for this entire message, the thing that I was struggling to land on because the weight of talking about God's wrath is so heavy,
my main point is this, that God's wrath will come to an end because his redemption will win.
This is the story of the book of Revelation. Just wait till we get to the last chapter.
Again, every tear is wiped from our eyes. There's no more mourning or sorrow or pain.
This is where the story is headed. But in between the crucifixion of Jesus,
the culmination of sin, death, and the grave showing its ugly head to the world,
crucifying an innocent savior.
It's between that moment and his return that we deal with this tension where we're waiting for his final redemption to come.
And in that, there is some experience of wrath, but God's wrath will come to an end because his redemption will win.
So let's revisit our therapy session from this morning.
I don't think the tension that we feel around the wrath of God is actually that we have a problem with holy and just and righteous judgment.
I don't think we have a problem with someone in a position of authority and morality executing judgment on somebody who's causing death and chaos to vulnerable people.
I think the issue that we have is we don't have an accurate view of our sinful actions and how it partners with the dragon to destroy God's good world.
We think our sin is not that big of a deal. I love C.S. Lewis has this illustration where he talks about the God that we want to create in our own image
is like a playful grandfather who winks at the grandson taking the fourth or fifth piece of candy, turning his eye.
Like we just want this God who doesn't really take seriously the way that we're behaving and leading to our own death and destruction.
We think our sin is not that big of a deal. We compare ourselves to others. We think other people deserve wrath, but we deserve grace.
If you don't believe me, just subscribe to this thing called "What's Happening Winchester in Frederick County" on Facebook.
See, some of you know.
There's this thing that happens, and it's so revealing to me as a pastor,
because somebody will post on there an article of somebody locally that's done something horrible and bad
and worthy of some consequences and punishment, and just the comments will be flooded with the most righteous people who have never done anything wrong ever.
Not wanting the system of justice to be played out for these individuals, but wanting them to be taken behind sheds and...
Right? Like, horrible, horrible things are said about these people.
Because that's in our heart of hearts, that's how we deal with our own guilt, our own judgment, our own sin.
We downplay the sin that's in our hearts, and we look and find somebody outside of us that we can point to and say, they're the ones that are deserving of wrath.
They're the ones that are deserving, that deserve judgment.
This is part of the thrust behind the Sermon on the Mount, where Jesus is saying to us, "You think adultery should be judged, but not lust."
And Jesus is saying, "Lust kills, steals, and destroys relationships and marriages and families just as bad as adultery does."
And you want to downplay your sinful actions that you hide in the darkness so that you can point to somebody whose sin has drug them into the light and say, "They deserve judgment. I deserve mercy."
You think murder should be judged, but not unforgiveness, gossip, or slander.
And Jesus is saying, "These things cause just as much damage and chaos."
And as a matter of fact, sometimes even worse because you can hide them and perpetuate them in the darkness for years and years and years.
Chaos and destruction behind you.
Jesus says, "You see the speck in your neighbor's eye and you have a four by four in yours."
I think, as I was wrestling and praying over this this week, I think God's wrath begins to become easier for us to handle when we realize the chaos and destruction that is created when we run from the light and hide in the darkness.
And if we're seriously honest with ourselves, all of us can bring to mind and heart things that we do, attitudes and actions and behaviors that we're hiding in the darkness,
that we've justified and explained away and said, "Don't ultimately cause anybody any harm."
And we know. We know that gossip and slander isn't victimless.
We know what our actions are doing. We know, and even if we don't, they are hardening our hearts towards God's righteousness.
They're hardening our hearts towards what good creation is intended to look like, what sacrificial love should look like in our relationships.
We run from the light. We hide in the darkness.
And so we have a problem with God's wrath because we have a misunderstanding of our sin and our participation with the dragon and his counterfeit kingdom.
I love how C.S. Lewis puts it. He says, "The more God loves you, the more determined he must be to pull you back from your way, which leads nowhere, into his way, which leads you where you want to go, to him."
This is why we must be prepared to find God implacably and immovably forbidding what may seem to us very small and trivial things.
Again, we do the comparison game. Our sin is small, other people's sin is big.
But as we understand God's love for us and his hatred towards the way in which sin destroys his good world, we can see the smaller things being pulled out.
And this is why, if you've ever had a relationship with somebody who's walked with the Lord for 50 years, and to you they look like the godliest person you've ever met, and you hear them talk and they're like, "I am the worst person you've ever met."
Because the more you walk with the Lord, the more your life is exposed to his light.
And the more you realize things that in your past you would have called small and insignificant, things that don't really impact anybody negatively, the more aware you become of how they destroy your soul and your relationships and God's creation.
And you see this progression even in the life of the Apostle Paul.
In one of Paul's first letters, he calls himself an apostle, right?
New believer had this mountaintop experience with God. God showed up in a flash of light, blinded him, healed him.
He's like, "God must really love me. I'm an apostle."
A few years later, he writes another letter, and he refers to himself as the least of the apostles.
He's walking with the Lord, and he's starting to understand the way in which his sin negatively impacts creation and his relationships all around him.
And the last letter that Paul writes, he refers to himself as the chief of sinners.
See the progression? As he walks with the Lord more and more, he realizes the weight of his sin and the negative impact it has on the world around him.
I think this is where the tension lies with us when it comes to the wrath of God. Do we fully understand how good and how loving and how good God's creation would be if sin didn't exist?
And do we fully understand our sin? Not just those who are, we can easily find a sin outside of us, where we can say that's causing death, chaos, and destruction.
But the sin inside of us, which leads me to the final question I want us to meditate on this morning. If God intends to destroy evil, what about the evil inside of me?
I think, yeah. The lust, the hatred, the unforgiveness, the greed, the idolatry, the pride, insert your issue here.
All of this contributes to the destruction of God's good creation.
And based on God's eternally wise and perfect redemption plan, it is all deserving of wrath.
In the Old Testament, the prophets talk about this wrath like a cup, God's cup being poured out on evil.
And the night Jesus was portrayed, he prayed, "Father, if possible, let this cup pass from me.
Nevertheless, not my will, but yours be done."
And just before he prayed, with this imagery of the cup of wrath being poured out, just before he prayed, "God, let this cup pass from me."
He offered his disciples a different cup.
He called it the cup of the covenant in his blood.
Then he goes to the cross to drink the cup of wrath.
So what about the evil inside of you?
What about the evil inside of me?
I think the Scriptures give us the picture that all sin will be dealt with.
That God's wrath will come to its completion, and his love will continue to exist for all eternity.
I think there's two cups that that wrath finds its completion in.
It's the cup of wrath, and it's the cup of the covenant in Christ's blood.
So is that something that you have received?
Have you accepted the grace and forgiveness of Jesus on your behalf?
Have you done what the people in Revelation 15 and 16 have yet to do?
Have you repented?
Have you acknowledged the ways in which you've contributed to the destruction of God's good world?
Have you turned from the cup of wrath and moved towards the cup of the covenant in Christ's blood?
A day will come, and it will not be announced, as we read in 2 Peter.
It will come like a thief in the night. A day will come when the last of God's wrath will be poured out.
And between now and then, there is a cup that sits on the table of churches all across the world.
The cup of the new covenant in His blood at the communion table.
It's an open invitation to all who would acknowledge their sin before a holy God
and trust the atoning work of Christ on their behalf.
So we're going to take communion in just a minute.
I'll give you time if you didn't have a chance to grab it.
And there's, I came up during that worship song because I wanted to say,
I felt like the worship set was very invitational.
That there's this idea that there's a place for me in heaven.
There's a seat for me at the table.
And as I was thinking about that invitation with my invitation here today,
I think there's really two main things that keep us from receiving that invitation.
The first is, and I think that this is fading away in our culture,
and I don't think it's a good thing that it's a fading away in our culture, but the first is maybe you're in here,
and you are like Paul, the chief of sinners.
And you are so aware of the bad patterns of behavior and sinful actions and attitudes that you have perpetuated all of your life,
and you might be thinking, "Yeah, Ryan, sure, there's a place at the table for most people, but not me."
Maybe you found yourself getting posted in one of those,
what's happening, Winchester, Frederick County, and you've read the comments of all the people saying all the horrible things about you,
and you can internalize, "Yeah, God's grace, God's forgiveness, that's great. It's not for me."
And I'm here to tell you that that's just your pride getting in the way of receiving a gift that your loving Father wants you to have.
So if you're here, and you haven't received Christ's forgiveness, and you think it's because you're not worthy, or you don't deserve it,
or you're too far gone, the cross cries a different answer.
For God so loved you that He gave His one and only Son.
And then the other side of that, people rejecting God's forgiveness, not receiving God's forgiveness.
This, I think, is becoming more prevalent in our culture, and that's, we just don't think we're that bad.
We think we're pretty good.
I can't, I don't deserve God's wrath. Other people might.
And so, if that's you, I would just ask you to sit with some of your worst days.
I ask you to think about some of the worst decisions you've made and some of the ways that that has negatively impacted people.
And some of those actions that we've perpetuated are going to negatively impact people for the rest of their lives.
And we've justified it and pushed it into the darkness. And we're good moving forward. We're pretty good people.
I think the cross of Jesus reminds us that even the smallest of sins that we justify away is worthy of God's wrath.
And if we haven't received the forgiveness of Jesus on the cross through the cup of the covenant in his blood,
a day will come when his wrath will be poured out.
And my invitation to you is don't let that day come for you.
That day could have already came for you 2,000 years ago on the cross.
Will you receive that forgiveness and that grace?
And I think for those of us that have already trusted in Christ, believers,
our response is to joyfully receive this cup with sober gladness
and join with the saints in Revelation who declare standing on top victoriously of the chaos waters.
Great and amazing are your deeds, O Lord, God Almighty.
Just and true are your ways, O King of the nations.
Who will not fear, O Lord, and glorify your name? For you alone are holy.
All the nations will come and worship you, for your righteous acts have been revealed in Jesus.
God's wrath is good because he is good. It is most clearly demonstrated in the person and work of Jesus.
God desires repentance and not rejection. He is patient, but that patience will come to an end.
Today, if you hear his voice, do not harden your heart.
So as we take communion...